howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is james lindsey
mathematician
free thinker skeptic southerner
author and independent thinker
hi jim great to be here yeah great to
have you on i've been a follower of your
tweet stream for quite a while
at conceptual james on twitter one of
the more interesting tweet streams out
there
and i heard about your new book reached
out to you i'm glad you agreed to come
on the show
james has published several books often
with co-authors
including how to have impossible
conversations which i read which is a
very good book
and another one everybody is wrong about
god which i
didn't know he had written until i did
my research for this podcast
and i'm going to read it soon james is
also
perhaps best known other than for his
books as
having participated with peter
bergassian and helen pluck rose i love
that name pluck rose what a wonderful
name
in a number of parody scholarly articles
uh basically sending up
post-modernist rhetoric several of which
were accepted for publication
including one that maintained and i love
this that the penis should be seen
not as an anatomical organ but as a
social construct
isomorphic to performative toxic
masculinity
hilarious the kind of horseshit that you
can get published out there
you guys must have had some fun with
that project oh lord did we ever the
laughter
oh i was even reading through one of our
papers again
this morning just briefly and i was like
i can't believe
the stuff we wrote and that they
accepted just so stupid it's so funny
some of it
so yeah that was that was i mean it was
a it was hard it was really difficult to
to learn that stuff kind of in real time
you know
none of us have a real background in any
of that crap
and so we had to learn that stuff in
real time and
face the reality of what it says which
is depressing when you start to realize
these people actually mean it
it's one thing to make it as jokes it's
another thing when these you realize
that the people doing this really mean
it
and then of course we tried to make them
funny so there was a lot of laughing i
mean i remember getting on the phone and
talking either with peter or with helen
to try to come up with ideas and just
laughing ourselves kind of sick
with stuff we might might try to write
about it was a good time
i just say both humorous and depressing
at the same time
did i recall that you wrote 20 and like
seven got accepted for publication and
another seven or so were in process at
the time you guys
revealed the stunt that's right yeah so
we wrote 20 in the span of about 10
months so it worked out to a paper every
two weeks which is pretty quick
and um seven of them were accepted four
actually got published of those seven
one of them got an award for excellence
in scholarship
and then yeah that's the one about dog
humping
oh god i love it oh it's the best it's
the best
you guys deserve a meta award right a
meta theory theory meta meta backwards
up and down reverse irony award for that
stunt i love it
we need like the anti-pulitzer or
something because the pulitzer put
itself in the toilet so we don't want
one of those anymore
yeah i guess i saw in fact somebody
referred to it as so-called squared
basically
alan sokol did something similar back in
the 90s
though not with quite the radical humor
that this particular
stunt had so well done gentlemen and
lady
well thank you i guess you're not
supposed to say lady anymore but
that right
that's right i'll say what i goddamn
well please kiss my ass
today we're mostly going to talk about
james's new book
who authored with helen pluck rose
titled cynical theories how
activist scholarship made everything
about race gender
and identity and why this harms
everybody
in which the authors carefully and in
great detail explore the history of
post-modernism
and how it is morphed into a series of
theories that underlie a lot of what we
see today
in the public sphere it'll be out at the
end of next month at least according to
amazon's that's still about right late
august
it's complicated it's mostly right
it got delayed because of the pandemic
it was supposed to come out in may
and then june and then that's august
25th they've stuck it with but they've
also said that when they start getting
enough copies from the printers
the the distribution will probably just
kind of start so the official date
is the 25th of august but it may start
trickling out a few weeks early
with the first you know however many
thousand copies they get their hands on
cool and as always we'll have a link to
the amazon
page on the episode page which you can
find at jimrutshow.com
interesting to note even though it's not
out yet it's already an
amazon bestseller and after reading it i
can see why this book
will be an indispensable reference for
people who want to deconstruct the
deconstructionists
it's extremely carefully written well
researched
has very good footnotes that take you to
back up for pretty much everything they
say
so if you want to become a anti-pomo
warrior
read this book people i'm
telling you it's well worth it
obviously i got a pre-publication copy
from james i actually did read the whole
book cover to cover and give it a major
thumbs up
thanks man i actually read it again the
other day and i was like wow this is a
whole lot more fair than i
was kind of afraid we were taking some
some swings toward the fences but it's
like wow this is really fair
yeah i was surprised frankly based on
some of the you say on your tweet
stream right
that you were just going to skewer the
on relentlessly but you
were actually very fair
no the goal was actually to give it a
very scholarly treatment and to explain
it to people in a very fair and clear
way
twitter's the arena but you know books
and publications
are another another matter you got to be
more serious uh twitter is good for
screwing around
plus i took the gloves off on twitter
and the path you know they started
setting cities on fire and saying that
that's okay because whiteness is
property and i was like okay gloves off
but we wrote the book before before they
started setting cities on fire so
um the gloves were still on a little bit
when we wrote it
it's probably good in in the in the long
run because it does need to be
treated fairly so that people will see
that we're not misrepresenting
the that they actually believe
which is which is so insane that it's
almost impossible to believe that they
really think that
and we'll get into that you know is it
actually insane or how the hell is it
that people come to believe that
horseshit
and do they actually right before we dig
into the meat of the matter
and i know you do talk about this
throughout the book i think it'd be
useful to lay out the alternative to
post-modernism
social justice quote unquote and all
that stuff
you know what you and helen lay out it's
kind of interwoven throughout the book
and there's a strong
argument about it at the end is that
liberalism
is the alternative right philosophical
liberalism and this is from your
introduction
philosophical liberalism is opposed to
authoritarian movements of
all types be they left-wing right-wing
secular or
theocratic why don't you talk a little
bit about that alternative because you
know it is true we still do have
issues that need to be resolved you know
there really is still
racism there really still is anti-gay
bigotry
women have not reached full operational
equality in the world
and though in the west we're getting
closer but there's another way to get
there rather than this
homo horse so maybe you could talk
just a little bit about the fact that
you're not saying
we shouldn't fight for increased social
justice
uncapitalized but the way to do it is
through
liberalism yeah that's right our
argument is ultimately about methods
uh we care if we have to use big words
we care about
the approach uh with with regard to
epistemology and ethics
and we try to make the sustained case
that the liberal approach
in the philosophical sense which is the
same philosophy that wrote the
declaration of independence in the
constitution of the us for example
that approach is the best we have
for doing epistemology and ethics
correctly so social justice is an ideal
and a lot of people don't understand
this because
the the freaking movement that's so
ascendant right now doesn't want anybody
to know it or doesn't want anybody
to remember it social justice is
something that has been of interest
to most societies throughout all of
history
except maybe totalitarian ones it's
certainly something that has been part
of the
say american experiment from the
beginning and then that's also imported
through most of
all of the rest of the advanced
democracies of the world
and so social justice has a as an ideal
just means a fairer more just society
and then the question becomes how do you
try to achieve it
and what we wanted to try to show people
is that there are lots of ways there are
lots of approaches there are religious
ideas about social justice you can go
back to walter rauschenbusch
we don't mention that in the book
specifically but you can you can go back
to walter rauschenbusch
turn of the 20th century and he was
trying to push the social gospel from a
uh baptist perspective so there are
religious approaches the term social
justice was invented by a jesuit priest
as a matter of fact so there were there
are religious approaches
there are liberal approaches obviously
that we argue for but there are also
communist approaches there are socialist
approaches there are materialist
approaches there are
lots and lots and lots of different
approaches even some conservative
approaches
can be seen as trying to establish a
more fair society
so there are lots of approaches so what
we want to try to do is take away the
illusion
that the current movement calling itself
social justice is the only way to go
about it
it uses a very specific method which is
critical theory infused with
post-modern epistemology and ethics and
so
we say no to that we say let's look at
other ideas so the liberal method
for us is superior as we make in the
case in the last chapter
because it works because it is a it's
not
what it's accused of being it's not
actually even necessarily
as much a political philosophy as people
think it is it is in fact
a method of resolving conflicts
between people in societies so if you
look at capitalism
what you have is people with property
rights once those are
enshrined that's a liberal philosophy
position is that people
have property rights once people have
property rights liberalism says well you
can do with your own property what you
want and you can work it out and you can
trade
pieces of your property for other pieces
of other people's property
and capitalism becomes the liberal
market
approach or economic approach and then
you can look at it in politics well you
get your vote everybody else gets their
votes so we're going to now use a
democratic way to
authenticate who our leaders are we're
not going to rely on the divine right of
kings anymore we're not going to rely on
who the warlord was that was able to
knock everybody down and they become the
leader
that's not how we do we're going to ask
the public and let the public decide and
democracy becomes the liberal approach
to resolving political conflict
if it's all written in the constitution
if you want to redress the government
for your grievances you can petition you
can peacefully protest you can always
peacefully assemble these
first you know these are core amendments
and
core foundational principles of a
liberal democracy that works
and then when it comes to understanding
ideas say if you and i have a different
idea
and we wanted to say well you say i'm
right and and
you know you say you say you're that
you're right and i say that i'm right
and so we both believe that we're right
we have to have a means of settling that
conflict and liberalism
offers a means it says let's go ask the
world or let's see who can give the
better
more reasoned argument if we can't get
the evidence
it doesn't say whose feelings are hurt
it doesn't care
then that's why it's so difficult
for people to accept because sometimes
the truth hurts and sometimes life isn't
fair
and it can be very difficult to accept
but the liberal approach to
making sense of the world is of course
that we can we can still be aware of the
idea
that there are realities of hurting
people or things being unfair that we
don't want to see
and liberal ethics uphold that but at
the same time
we say look we're going to look at the
evidence and the evidence can include
that hurt feelings are bad and we're
going to look at
the the best arguments and we're not
just going to give in
because somebody's making a demand or
somebody's claiming offense
or or whatever else we actually have to
make reasoned arguments we actually have
to appeal to the evidence
and so we have these different methods
to try to resolve
conflicts between individuals that come
up within a society
and our case is that if we want a more
fair more just socially just society
we need liberalism to keep making the
gains that it's made
for the past several centuries rather
than
saying oh wow we're actually achieving
real progress now so let's abandon the
thing
that got us there which is what the
current movement is
asking us to do it wants to throw away
liberalism
and use its own radical approach which
is
i mean we don't get into it deeply in
the book but it's actually known as
liberationism
or liberation philosophy which comes out
of the
the frankfurt school of uh critical
theory which is neo-marxism if you
if you must know yeah marcus and those
assholes right
yeah marcus in particular um you know
you can dip into stuff that adorno
wrote and of course max horkheimer's
relevant you can dip into these guys
but marcusa was actually extremely
relevant to what we're seeing today
a lot of people don't realize this but
we all know who these these antifa
assholes are running around and these
antifa guys
well they are basically if you take
herbert marcuso's philosophy especially
on repressive tolerance and franz
fannin's ideas
he's a french psychoanalyst that was
studying the uh colonial condition
if you take those two people and you mix
them together you get antifa that's what
it is that's where their ideas come from
that's why they think they're justified
in behaving in the world but the way
they do
so marcusa is definitely his presence is
definitely felt
uh throughout the world and it's last
time he had a massive following was in
the mid-1960s he wrote repressive
tolerance in 1965
lo and behold 1967 and 1968 we have
massive riots including race riots
that end up you know wrecking american
cities for example
even detroit hasn't even recovered from
yep indeed in fact we talk about
liberalism and the fact that it has
always been imperfect but continuing to
improve
and we have to acknowledge that right
you know thomas jefferson wrote the
beautiful words
all men are created equal but he was
also a slave holder oh well
right but on the other hand in 1808 the
u.s government abolished the slave trade
you know
britain abolished slavery not too long
thereafter united states spent 600
000 deaths equal to about five million
at our current
population to end slavery etc etc
and we'll talk about some of the other
progress of liberalism but to show how
deep it is in the dna of liberalism to
think this way i love to point people
to a mid 19th century essay by john
stuart
mill called the subjection of women
in which he applied liberalism about as
radically as you could at that time to
argue for the fact that women
needed to be liberated and that their
subjugation by the patriarchy
was wrong and inconsistent with
liberalism
i'd love to point people back who think
of liberalism as somehow retrograde
to one of the core thinkers of
liberalism bill
in that essay yeah mill is is one of my
my philosophical heroes when people kind
of ask me what kind of a liberal are you
you know
i you know i think highly of jefferson
and i think highly of course is lock and
pain and all of these people
but you know i really resonate with mill
so i think
million liberals are known as
traditional liberals now or something
like that so
okay that's me uh if i have to take a
label and i i fully agree
it's like the point of liberalism was to
say
let's start with some very fundamental
principles about
about humanity the universal humanity
and
the the recognition that human beings
are also autonomous individuals who have
their own minds
their own intellects their own capacity
for reasoning in their own capacity to
make moral decisions for themselves
they are have the capacity of course if
they wish
to join groups say religious groups but
those are a matter of their
private conscience and their personal
volition and so they cannot be compelled
by the power say of the state to have
certain beliefs and that we call that
secularism
and so these views were literally
the ones that allowed us to untie the
knots
of injustices like patriarchy racism
slavery homophobia we can go down the
list judith butler one of the
big big famous theorists in in the
critical vein now um
judith butler calls it that exasperated
etc when you try to name all of them
all the different oppressions that they
that they focus on and so
liberalism turned out to be the thing
that moved us away
from a long human history
in which different cultures arose of
course and they had different approaches
to these different questions
and some of them did better than others
on different
aspects of them but none of them really
had anything
like universal humanity respect for the
individual
to understand that each person has their
own mind and none of them had
a robust and impartial or as impartial
as possible
of course nothing's perfect method of
resolving conflicts between individuals
within their societies
that that could match with liberalism
which is why when liberalism came onto
the scene
you started to see massive advances in
progress as you notice you know
jefferson writes all men are created
equal in 1775 or six
he goes on you know he's a slave owner
he struggles with this but the slave
trade is is outlawed
by 1808 and then you know
by 1863 emancipation is
is had and then again chipping away
over time a lot of people i think of
these these
oppressions i should say so a lot of
people think and we say this in the book
a lot of people think that it's a
reasonable argument to point back at the
way that liberalism it wasn't
people have this unrealistic expectation
like that liberalism just showed up on
the scene
and then bam everything's liberal
everything's great everybody's free
everything works out no it's it's
it's a process it's a conflict
resolution system that allows you to
start fixing problems
so it would be ridiculous to think oh
well people thought of liberalism now
everything's liberal
and that's sort of the way the critics
of liberalism think about it
and say well look at how how badly it's
failed
without tallying up its ridiculous
successes alongside of that which are
unmatched in human history and that no
other
society has ever produced and i'm not
saying some paying to
to necessarily the united states the
same philosophies applied in other
places as you noted
britain outlawed slavery before the
united states did okay so the same
principles applied in another context
worked there a little bit faster it's
not like i'm saying oh well we're the
most magical people ever
no that's asinine what makes sense
though is that these principles
when applied literally anywhere in the
world that they get applied start
creating
positive changes that reduce oppression
and subjugation
that increase flourishing that increase
people's
economic standing and freedom and
ability to move within that system
it's just the best system for resolving
the problems
of of human conflict that we've come up
with not to say that it's perfect
but that's the whole point you mentioned
that liberalism actually only works
because it's willing to take criticism
of itself and improve
what it's already doing so if you look
at liberalism as a kind of philosophy
it's silly to say whether it's perfect
or not that's not the point the point as
a philosophy is that it's willing to
take self-criticism and say
how can i do better at every stage with
whatever i'm doing now so if the
question is slavery how
the ideals got written down all men are
created equal
how do we start living up to that so we
start living up to it with abolition and
then later on you hear martin luther
king stand up and you say
you hear him appeal i should actually
back up
before abolition you had frederick
douglass stand up it was very
widely distributed this fourth of july
just just this month
and you heard frederick douglass stand
up and appeal to that promise in the
constitution and said where is it if we
have slavery where is it
show us that promise and then people did
ten years later they did
and then martin luther king stands up in
the early 1960s and he says
really if we're all supposed to be equal
where is it show us that promise show us
that promise
and a few years later the civil rights
act was passed in other words
we did we started to live up to that
promise but that promise had to be there
it had to be made uh stable and and
something to be
to appeal to in order for us to be able
to
live up to it and appealing to living up
to it rather than tearing it apart
is what enabled us to make progress
consistently and steadily
over painful decades and painful
centuries
and get to a place that's i mean except
for a lunatic fringe
undeniably better for literally
everybody
great well said well said one last thing
before we get
into the meat of it and let's try to
keep this short so we do have time to
get into the details of the book
if we think about fighting against
illiberalism
as one of the core calls of humanity i
would say so at least
look at the 20th century the three big
cusps of the 20th century world war one
world war ii in the cold war
while they also had obviously some big
power politics and self-interest etc
could
be broadly construed as being liberalism
versus ill liberalism
right in our current world we have
illiberalism
of both the right and the left you know
i'd argue that a piece of like
donald trump is at least a want to be a
liberal
but fortunately so incompetent and so
driven by his
all-galaxy narcissism isn't very good at
it
we have other liberals more maybe more
effective
maybe not some of the white supremacists
some of the
wacko thinking like neo-reactionary dark
enlightenment etc
why did you choose to focus on leftist
liberalism in this book
rather than illiberalism more generally
well
it's a big problem and a big question
and you're absolutely right that it's a
both side's problem
but in the scope of a book you do have
to have
something to focus upon and you should
probably focus on that which you're
genuinely expert in and that you've
studied so
we were genuinely expert in this
particular aspect of illiberalism the
the left version that's that's coming
forth in the so-called
woke or social justice movement and so
we had to talk about our expertise and
the thesis that we wanted the thesis is
actually quite narrow
of the book the thesis is that
post-modernism infected this particular
radical leftist line of thought and made
it something very difficult to argue
against
if you and this is how that happened so
you know we had to pick a focus and we
wrote the
wrote to that focus also our feeling is
as we we explained and i think the
introduction to the book but it may be
in the last chapter we
we feel like the the left has
abandoned its principle of liberalism
whereas conservatism has
always kind of dithered about its
commitment to liberalism
and so we feel as denizens of the left
also being relevant but we we feel that
the left in the sense that it has
abandoned what it
should have been standing for has
committed a sin
that needs to be addressed and in fact i
would insist it
while it's all complicated in its
reciprocal and everything else that
the stuff from the left is driving a
great deal of the reactionary side from
the right
and that if the left cleans its house up
and sanity prevails on the broad left
with of course everybody having their
lunatic fringe
that a lot of the tensions of the
culture war are likely to calm down
so we we set our sights on the left
because we're there because we know it
better because we need a specific focus
and because
while donald trump for example is an
enormous irritant and i think that the
right wing has been doing a bunch of
for
40 plus years now that's uh its own
threat to liberalism
the outburst of behavior from the left
is a genuine
threat that's driving the problem as it
exists in the world today
also they've stolen our academies and as
academics we're pretty pissed about that
all right you open up the book with
talking a fair amount
about the history of post-modernism now
frankly i think that
it's very interesting to read but i
don't want to go into copious detail on
it here but
for our audience give enough of the
history of post-modernism
to go forward and then we'll talk a
little bit about your two principles and
four themes
okay great yeah so post-modernism is a
movement that actually kind of arose in
art and literature
maybe the 1940s and it started to
question
i guess the best way to think about it
is i started to question the the rigid
structure and rules
that would construct art if you wanted
to get into the proper history of it
so you'd see people doing experimental
nonsense like taking a book
and then taking every noun that they
come across in the book and replacing it
with
the the next noun uh in that dictionary
and then trying to extract meaning out
of whatever
results this is a postmodern art project
on literature for example
or you would see people with music
saying oh well you're supposed to do
this kind of a thing with this
musical scales so we're going to invert
that so you'd often see people
this is key to the idea inserting
arbitrary rules
that would be normally considered out of
bounds
specifically to point out the fact that
rules are arbitrary
and so that's sort of the the the ethos
of post-modern thought that led it to
challenge boundaries and challenge
expectations
so then in the 1960s or really in 1950s
into the 1960s you had this
spate of french philosophers who were
very caught up in structuralism
as a way of understanding the world
which has been since discredited
that's the idea essentially that
language and the way we use language
structures
how we think and therefore structures
all of society it doesn't quite work
that way
but uh they got very invested in
studying the way that language
and power are interrelated with one
another
and they became very interested in
seeing the way that the culture
is produced through uses of language
representation
imagery power and again started to want
to show that the rules
are a arbitrary and b
that they actually contain the seeds of
structural oppressions that
appear in society so you had big
thinkers like
jack derida the famous post-structural
linguist
and you had michel foucault who claimed
he was something like a historian
but what he really did was archaeologies
as he called them in genealogies where
he tore
up history to show how thought had
kind of big regimes of truth he called
them or epistemes
and these things dictated how people
would think and then look how
wrong they were and look how terrible
all of these things led to
you know in in practice and so the the
conclusion of these guys would be
well how could we possibly think that
we're right now and how could we
possibly think that our words have
genuine meaning
that anybody can understand that the
author can have intent
and it's kind of this whole mind-blowing
mind-expanding
way as foucault would have put it it was
about expanding
the potentialities of being so meaning
that
you know if you if you break the rules
of how you think you're supposed to
think about the world
if you deconstruct them by showing that
they're arbitrary
and that there are other alternatives
then you can live in different ways
that the current rules of society don't
allow you to
which if you're gay or into rough sex
like
foucault was there's some credit to be
to be given to that claim but if you're
talking about you know the
potentialities of
being being limited by gravity um it's
not so much
but they uh to kind of wrap up used all
of this
this thinking this dissatisfaction
with how the world was going and we can
talk about that historically too because
it's actually interesting in a moment
but they used it to forward the most
important idea that they have is that
all knowledge all claims to truth
are ultimately the result of political
processes and therefore are actually
means of forwarding power politics and
not means of
trying to describe what's real in the
world whatsoever
interesting yeah confess until recently
i had
not paid too much attention to
post-modernism
mostly for that reason especially its
denigration of science i go what the
assholes right
if you can't see that science is a
fundamentally different way of knowing
than anything that came before it
and is qualitatively different then
whatever it is you're thinking is
obviously horseshit right
and so this theory that there is no
objective knowledge there is no
objective truth
while it's funny i sympathize with it at
one level because even my beloved
science
those of us have dug into the sociology
of science know that it goes down wrong
roads
it does various things that it shouldn't
but it
has a built-in intersubjective and
inter-objective mechanism for
reconverging to what is correct and it
seems that these clowns miss that
somehow i don't know how
that's actually a really good summary of
it i can tell you how
it's that they well there's a couple of
reasons if we can get into the
psychological side which is i think that
they
legitimately were just jealous of the
prestige and power of science
and they used that jealousy to do as
foucault called them archaeologies and
genealogies where they nitpicked it like
oh look here's a failure oh look here's
a failure
so where you say that you can sympathize
and they you can see where the sociology
of science has done this wrong
it's got that wrong they they cherry
pick that heart
that part and then they skip the part
where
it reconverges entirely because that's
not useful to complaining about the
thing that they're jealous of
and angry at the other the more
theoretically grounded reason that they
express in their writing is that they
believe that well
they look at the sociology of science
and they say well obviously this is a
social process that decides which
methods are are valid and which methods
are not
which truths are valid which truths are
not since that's a social process and
you can see what a dirty social process
it's been especially historically it
must be just
dirty power politics that decided which
methods and so foucault's point for
specific to be specific was
that whether or not a claim about
objective truth is
actually true doesn't matter he
didn't say that it's not he said that it
doesn't matter if it is or not because
it ignores the more relevant point that
the politics of how we decided it or
what we need to put our focus on
and so they had this very nihilistic
despairing kind of perspective
where they're you know sort of woe is me
and
um everything must be politics because
i think honestly because their politics
weren't working out these were marxists
who were staring upon the
failures of marxism throughout the world
they were staring at the failures
of communism to to affect good things
they're looking at the the
deaths the genocides the reactionary
pushbacks that led to fascism and
they're just seeing that the communist
revolutions weren't working
they did have a soft spot in their heart
for for mao they were big fans of mao
occasionally and sometimes they would
change their mind and not be you know
being in the 1950s and getting into the
1960s
uh their buddy pol pot was hanging out
with them there in the sarbane and
that's sort of like the culture
that they had happening and then he went
back to cambodia that went real well
and so yeah they had this
whole view that that
truth and falsity don't matter because
the politics of determining what's true
and false are the really interesting
thing
and of course when you start looking at
it and you start feeding that kind of
crap to activists and
and people who frankly don't have the
chops to do science because it's hard
uh to do science you give them a tool
that's just like
you know the best thing ever if they
want to start chopping down at the field
that's taken seriously where their
fields are not taken as seriously
contextually the humanities had been
losing a lot of ground
in terms of being like real academia as
science really rose to prominence and
through the you know the logical
positivism movement
you can think back to the 1950s and all
of those tv shows you know so we will
change the world with science and they
have that very you know
voice we would associate with just being
you know promotional crap now
and so they they were in that meloo
reacting against that
thinking well what about this nonsense
we do why is it why are we not important
can't get lost on you how often foucault
pointed out that one of his points was
to be
an intellectual rock star in the french
tradition and to do what he did to
attract pretty boys
and he said it more than once so um
you know there was this whole edgy
avant-garde let's break down the
establishment
mentality that was just happening and
they get caught up in it
how people decided to pick it up envy i
can't i can't
figure out another reason they're
envious of the sciences saw tools to
tear them apart
off to the races interesting and
good point about the fact that it was in
the face of the decline of marxism i
don't remember who said it was one of my
favorite quotes is that by the
early 1990s the last marxists on earth
were the
members of the english departments of
elite american universities
that's right and most of them were
feminists and that's actually key right
because that's who picked this stuff up
and ran with it it was feminists who
were trying to blame
capitalism for the patriarchy you know
we're talking feminists in like the
1970s
and so on as you're saying oh these
these kind of very marxist feminists
were starting to pick up these
post-modern ideas because
many of their attempts to deconstruct
gender and even to poke biological sex
were just getting
railroaded by biology they just they're
out of touch with reality social
constructivism
is a thing but it only goes so far and
they want it to go 100
and that's that doesn't work and so they
started to pick this stuff
up and it started to get more and more
radical with the w
with what they're trying to attempt and
science wasn't having it
you started to have people coming up in
the 70s and 80s with stuff like
um strong objectivity that was sandra
harding in the 1980s she was trying to
say that
that you know we need a feminist
empiricism that brings a womanly
perspective into science because it's
always been
excluded and it's just when you start
doing that
science becomes your enemy and you need
a tool to deconstruct it's
uh as they would say it's hegemony and
there's post-modernism laying there
one truth is as good as any other and
every truth is political and if it's
been excluded
that means it's problematic and it needs
to be interrogated
perfect fit for these radical feminists
who
then imported this idea that they really
should have left
left on the on the cutting room floor of
french philosophy
because the french didn't take this
stuff up the french were like what is
this crap
no yeah interesting yeah i think you
just hit on it in passing but i'm going
to
call it out because it's so important
you say yeah it has something
of merit to it but they go too far 100
percent
you know language i like to use is both
and right it is true that the sociology
of science is important
it is true that the decisions we make
and the institutional mechanisms we've
put in place
for the allocation of dollars to
different research disciplines
how careers are had in science what are
the barriers to the access to scientific
careers
are all important questions but but
the inner core of the scientific engine
to my mind is really sound yes we can
improve a little
bit the engine but there's a big big
difference to the
the control mechanisms around science
and the inner engine
of tentative step-by-step based on
falsifiability
of theories backed up by data and or
experiment etc
that is unchallenged to my mind i've
seen no challenge that makes any sense
while the issues of sociology of science
and indeed the power
relationships and politics around what
science chooses to study and
particularly how money flows
are indeed important so what we really
need to do is keep both
in our minds not go to this nihilistic
crazed view that it's
that it's all power because it's not
that's right yeah both the the critical
theory tradition and the post-modern
tradition
uh have have ways to confuse people
about this and of course the the
feminists would have been
been aware following marcus in
particular of the critical theory
tradition uh much of the marxist thought
of the time which
feminism had taken up a lot of was was
infused with that
and so it would say well you have to
look at what's hegemonic and
what people are creating the the
hegemony what ideologies are they
pushing
and so then they would do these same
kind of archaeological or genealogical
digs and say hey
look well you know the people who used
to explore the arctic and find out
information about the arctic these these
geographers had to be manly tough men
and that we really did make decisions
you know in the
late 19th century about truth about the
arctic based on how studly the person
was and how many you know
you know how many polar bears they could
kill or some stupid thing
before anybody had any idea of how to
how to make scientific determinations
about the world
and then they just import that forward
and say well that must have set up a
hegemony that's kept women out all along
because you know on some level it was
used as a justification
and on other levels it was one we were
chipping away at but if you only look at
the dark side of it you get mad
and with the postmodern thought the idea
is that
following for example either foucault or
derrida there's two different
constructions that get you there that
they both get you there the idea is that
the discourse is constructed
around a thing so the scientific
enterprise are constructed by the people
who create them
and that their political biases are what
create
how those discourses work and thus the
power dynamics within that sociology so
they would say from a postmodern
perspective that
if there is some problem in the
sociology
of science say sexism or whatever that
it must come from the science itself
because the discourses of the science
are what are structuring that sociology
because of that french structuralism
stuff
and so the point of post-modernism being
post-structuralist is to tear down
those power dynamics you know they look
at the power dynamic and the sociology
they say it must be coming from all of
the relevant discourses that inform that
sociology
therefore you have to start tearing
those apart and deconstructing them to
get rid of the power so they think that
the way people talk about the actual
science
it's a confusion makes the sociology of
that relevant science
a problem which is why you see people
liking computers saying well we can't
use
you know phrases like master slave or
whatever you can't
blacklist and whitelist things because
that language gives a subtle thing that
makes people uncomfortable
of different races or sexes or genders
or sexualities or whatever so we have to
be very careful with our language
because the language is going to
structure
how the sociology is and that sociology
is therefore becomes kind of the
the e-meter that lets you figure out if
the language
the discourses themselves are poisoned
it's a very stupid way to think
it's really a very it's like it's
insulting too
it's insulting that's actually because
it assumes everybody's a bunch
of pussies right
with false consciousness yeah all
that right
and we'll get to that later especially
when we talk about critical race theory
but you know i believe that this whole
approach has done a huge disservice for
the so-called marginal folks right
this isn't how you solve the problem
becoming neurotic and
seeing boogeyman every where but
let's wrap up the history part a little
bit by
doing a relatively brief review of your
two principles
and your four themes and then let's move
on
right so we kind of condensed all of
that history into identifying two
core principles of postmodern thought
the first is that knowledge is socially
constructed
generally in service of power and the
second goes into that power aspect
more specifically and says that dominant
groups within society have had the
ability to
construct knowledge and therefore their
own power
and so there's an ethical imperative to
take apart powerful discourses so we
called the first of those that there's
no access to objective truth and
knowledge is just socially constructed
the post-modern knowledge principle we
call the second one
that there's a political power valence
to the whole project that needs to be
unmade the post-modern political
principle
so those two core principles kind of
define what post-modern thought is and
we wanted to
to narrow it down to that so we could
see in future generations of thought
that those principles are still
consistently showing up
we identify four core themes of
postmodern
thought and application and those if i
can name them all in one go
those are the blurring of boundaries so
trying to take any categories that you
might
be able to think of whether it's man and
woman whether it's knowledge and
storytelling
and blur the boundaries between them so
that everything kind of becomes the same
thing
second one is the almighty power of
language or an exaggerated focus on the
power of language we just described
that the the belief that words almost
work like magic spells to structure the
sociology of a thing
a third one would be cultural relativism
which would be both in terms of
morals so ethical relativism moral
relativism as you'd hear you can't judge
one culture
there's ethics from the position of
another culture which it imported from
some of the early moves in anthropology
and then
also epistemological relativism that you
can't judge one knowledge system from
within another knowledge
system so as they phrase it though ways
of knowing one way of knowing
like science can't bear upon the
validity of another way of knowing like
witchcraft
uh because they're they're relative and
that they're products of their
their distinct cultures and so the one
can't speak to the other
and then the fourth is the dissolution
so we talked earlier about liberalism
it's a dissolution of the belief in a
universal humanity
and the dissolution of the belief in the
autonomous individual people are
products of their social groups and holy
products of their social groups
and so it comes down to defining how
those social groups are defined with the
original post-modernist it would have
been
particular time and place and culture so
you know
france 1960 would have been maybe a
thing or france and the late medieval
period
would have been a thing and this over
time has evolved to where your
uh cultural groups have now been wedged
into identity categories
though the original post-modernist
wouldn't have thought that way but the
point was that
you're not an individual you're a french
person in the medieval period
and that's how you think like there's
this consciousness that goes with being
in which culture at what time you happen
to be and then there's no universal
humanity because
one group can't genuinely understand
each other because they have completely
different ethics and completely
different
epistemologies so they can't even
properly speak
to one another so there's this erasure
of all of the fundamental principles
of liberalism like understanding the
world clearly
uh universal principles of of humanity
and viewing people as individuals and
saying that yeah we can make some
universal judgments about right and
wrong
and no you know we don't have to get
tricked by word games there is a
fundamental reality beneath it all that
we can understand
and talk about on shared terms
very good i often will describe it as
people claiming that
both witch doctors and johns hopkins
hospital are equally good at curing
cancer you know what the right
how do people believe that horseshit but
as you say in the book
eventually kind of the internal
contradictions of
this abstract french theory driven
post-modernism
started to wind down you know people
eventually said all right maybe it's
intellectually cute and curious to probe
but
it doesn't really lead anywhere useful
and then you talk about
what you call the post-modernism's
applied turn
where it was reformed in various ways
and simplified i would say in some ways
and then move forward so let's move
quickly here
to the post-modernism's applied term
yeah so that really happened and if you
want to throw earmarks on it you could
say that post-modernism was 1970
and the applied turn was 1990. a lot
happened in the mid and late 1980s
and what happened ultimately was that
the remnants of the radical activists
from the 60s and 70s these marcusian
activists the critical theorists
liberation black power
radical feminists they had lost a lot of
their clout and they had lost a lot of
their ability to argue because people
just kind of got tired with the whole
power dynamic thing all the time
and they found post-modern tools and so
you had a couple of
a couple of thinkers prominently in the
late 1980s or mid-1980s who started to
figure out
well if we say that you can't
deconstruct
the experience of oppression but if you
start using post-modern tools to
deconstruct
power now we have a very actionable
understanding of both post-modern theory
and critical theory that we can put into
application
and they explicitly did that they
combined that
very radical uh critical approach
with postmodern tools by setting aside
the idea of universal deconstruction and
saying no
the experience of oppression is real and
only somebody with privilege could
possibly deconstruct it
so let's simplify post-modernism down to
deconstructing those
powers that create oppression and we
take oppression off the table
so now you can't deconstruct race
because
race is a site of oppression and so now
you start to see this identity politics
very explicitly becoming the cultural
groups
that are relevant to the postmodern
principles and themes
that's kind of the world we're kind of
living in now right the supplied
post-modernist epoch or at least this
disease that seems to be rampant in the
world
so let's now move on to where you start
to dig into the first of these
applied post-modernist theories which is
post-colonial
theory and early in that chapter you
make a very key distinction which
frankly
i was not aware of so it was a good
education for me too
which is the identity politics when
looked at deeply from
theory is actually deeply cynical it
appears
you can correct me if i'm wrong about
this that the postcolonialists and
critical
race theory people don't actually
believe in identity essentialism
you discovered that they used a term
called strategic essentialism
which strikes me as a very cynical way
to have proceeded
could you perhaps you know either
correct me and or expand
on this concept of strategic
essentialism
as one of the base concepts of applied
post-modernism
sure yeah i mean there's a little bit to
correct in a little bit to
to say that you've got correct already
and expand upon
so the idea of strategic essentialism i
mean it's a useful concept it's a useful
tool
uh to fight against power that's
basically controlling you
and so it means to adopt the negative
stereotypes
about yourself that some powerful group
is applying to you
and to do so in a self-aware which means
slightly ironic way
to use it as a weapon of resistance to
that power
so you could imagine for example we
could flash back to the 1950s and you
have the
you know stereotypical 1950s white boss
talking
however about how he thinks black people
are stupid and lazy or whatever
and then he tells his black employee to
go do whatever
job go sweep the floor you know or
whatever and then the black person
responds well i don't know boss i'm too
stupid and lazy
and so that would be an example of using
strategic essentialism to fight
power and i think there's some
legitimacy to it because it calls people
out on
on applying unjust stereotypes like
everything it can go too far
so the idea really got defined by a
postcolonial theorist
named gayatri spivak in the mid-1980s
and spivak was a uppercast indian woman
who decided to start writing about how
horrendous colonialism was and
um really took a lot i mean she cites
foucault on nearly every page of her
of her work also draws very heavily on
derrida and derrida is more relevant for
this
strategic essentialism because the idea
is oh well there's binary
hierarchies of power and everything that
that we encounter in life
and so what strategic essentialism is is
that we're going to now
preserve those hierarchies but we're
going to reverse the power
so we're going to flip it backwards
that's the way that spivak
characterized the idea and took it
further and so
now for example if you say well there's
a power dynamic between men and women
that you know men are dominant over
women she would say well we're going to
preserve that
hierarchy that men and women are
different but we're going to reverse the
power so now it's girl power
now now now women are the ones that that
are to have
power women domination is great and you
can do this with whatever
set of identity factors or whatever that
you want to do so it became this
site upon which they had to do two
things and the cynical part that you're
pointing at
is that they wanted to preserve the
existing hierarchy where
if we compare that to liberalism the
point is to chip away at the
meaningfulness of that hierarchy
they want to preserve the hierarchy and
then they want to try to reverse the
direction
of of power in it and this actually in
some sense is why
as many people have noticed and it
pardoned my frustration with it but
the the the kind of social justice
activists get literally
everything backwards
and it's because they're preserving the
hierarchies and reversing the power but
the problem is that the hierarchy itself
is the issue and you can't just
arbitrarily reverse every bit of power
and create you know the change that you
want
so with the post-colonial theorists what
they do is they said well that the west
used to say we're we're great and you're
barbarous we're smart and you're stupid
we're
scientific and you're superstitious the
west is better than the east and so the
west constructs itself as superior and
the east is inferior and this could be
extended to the global south as well
and then liberalism said hey maybe we
should think of people as people
wherever they live
and try to work from there and this this
apparently was intolerable to these
radical activists who wanted to
strategically essentialize
and they said no let's reconstruct it
that the east is
the the poor oppressed entity by the
west and that the west is actually evil
colonizers but let's establish that the
west did use science and it is the
property of the west and let's get this
backwards completely
so we can say oh they use their science
to destroy africa which
if anybody has any sense in their
freaking head if you want to get like
working wells and you want to get a city
up and operating you've got to use
science so you're not helping freaking
africa by saying it's white stuff to do
science
um but that's where it comes from
preserve the hierarchy and flip the
power
which is strategic essentialism uh
thanks to gayatri spivak
yeah interesting what a weird move and
it's so strange that people
buy this stuff right it's like what you
also talked in that section of the book
about how
decolonizing fears or they are now
also
have decided that philosophy is
bad because it gives a special place to
reason
could you talk about that a little bit
yeah
the idea is that they they genuinely
believe
that everything is a property of the
culture that invented it
and so when you say that the
enlightenment took place in the european
context
for whatever set of historical
contingencies that led to that fact of
history
you say the enlightenment took place in
in we the elevation of reason the
development of scientific
reasoning all happened in the european
context mostly by white people mostly by
men because of the other historical
contingencies around
those decisions they they believe that
that locks
white western maleness into the
scientific and reason-bearing or
philosophical processes
and therefore those are the property of
white western men and they're not
the property of say black africans or
indigenous people in in south america or
whatever else and therefore
therefore those those are properties
that are
are tied to a specific culture and for
it's so hard to even freaking explain
this it's so stupid
and so for say people to go to africa or
to south america or to anywhere in the
world that doesn't have science and try
to teach them science
is literally a colonial act of trying to
change their culture to value white and
western things
rather than just trying to teach them
very effective methods to understand the
world
coming to africa to teach them to rely
on reason if that's what it was
would be seen as an act of colonial
aggression that tries to erase
african cultures that have always
thought differently it's
in some sense in that way very
conservative because it's like no leave
the noble savages
alone don't change anything about them
even if it would be to their benefit you
can't change that
because that's as they say colonialism
it's so mental that it's almost
impossible to talk about without kind of
just getting pissed off
i understand that exactly and of course
what i love about it is how ignorant
some of the assumptions are even you
know that reason
is white right anyone who knows anything
about the history of greek philosophy
knows that it is
believed with some reason that the
antecedents of greek philosophy or
reason was finally
defined at least in such a way that it
came into the western tradition
actually came from egypt right at least
so it appears and so it's actually an
egyptian
invention that was refined and written
down
essentially by the greeks and further
for a long time it was essentially the
property of the greeks and then to a
lesser degree the romans but there are
lots of white people who had never had
any exposure to this kind of thinking
right
the britons the celts the vikings they
never heard any of this horse until
much later you know 1000 a.d perhaps
that aristotelian philosophy slowly
start to penetrate
europe so it came from egypt it was
processed by the greeks it was refined a
bit by the romans though not very much
and then
was carried forth in a kind of flattened
form by
scholastic catholicism and only
gradually
expanded around into allegedly the white
realm
so and then it expanded to the rest of
the world and why did it expand to the
rest of the world
well those who listen to my show know
that i have one word
which i use as my razor for ideas and
that is
are they useful right and as it turned
out
reason is useful
that's correct and so to understand how
how off the track because what you just
described is absolutely correct
and to understand how off the track the
thought
process here in the the whether we're
going to call it
social justice or postcolonial in this
case but it's all of the theories
how off the track it is it doesn't care
all it cares about is who was able to
apply it in
in the service of what they call
systemic power and that systemic power
applies
only in the current system which is post
enlightenment progress i guess the
modern world actually
that which follows the late medieval
period going forward
so that's the only context and they say
well who had
these ideas and who was able to apply
systemic power with them
white people you know in a eurocentric
context mostly men
therefore these ideas are the province
of white western men and to use them
and pushes white western culture onto
everybody else
because again following foucault with
his truth regimes that established a
truth regime
that was supposed to be fitting for the
european context in the early and mid
modern periods and then they decided
that they were going to try to force it
upon the rest of the world
which was other cultures that couldn't
have been despoiled by
such terrible things as useful reason
and applicable science uh
it's such it's like it's not even
just a stupid way to think and just a
terribly narrow way to think it's again
very conservative in a weird way like
that the world
should have remained in its pre-modern
feudal state and any aberration from
that any deviation from that is an
oppression
that's intolerable and and has to be
unmade
that that's genuinely their thought
process because they're obsessed with
the systemic
power that getting right answers to the
to questions about the world provided
europeans primarily white european men
yeah it's horseshit you know a
good friend of mine is
cto of a company that's providing solar
electricity to remote
villages in africa and i can tell you
from listening to him
that the libido for having electricity
in remote villages in africa is huge
right these people don't feel oppressed
by having electricity for the first time
and then satellite internet
and being connected to the world being
able to look something up on google
scholar
that's hugely empowering to them and
where the these people are
here's another one of my thoughts a
little bit about neocolonialism
colonialism theory whatever the hell it
is
the brits england was the great
colonizing power
right everybody likes to criticize the
english but hey what happened to the
english right they had the brightons way
back yonder who were attacked and almost
exterminated by the celts
who were invaded by the romans when the
romans started to collapse and withdraw
in 400 a.d
soon thereafter the angles and the
saxons from lowland germany attacked and
substantially took over
england the danes came down and captured
the
northern third of england dean law for a
couple hundred years
then the normans came in and imposed a
truly hideous occupation
and built a whole new aristocracy that
suppressed the out of the english
and so the history of england has been
wave after wave after wave of
colonization suppression domination etc
and yet they seem to come out all right
out of it
it took me a long time to figure out how
these people think it really took me a
long time to figure out this mystery
and the the answer is is that
all of that stuff doesn't matter because
systemic power
in the modern era hadn't been invented
yet they really think that they
only care like the world the beginning
of time for them and sometimes i see
they post on
instagram these kind of memes and
they post really they
say words like the since the beginning
of time white people have had all the
power in the world
so they literally think that the
beginning of time
was the enlightenment in the the
beginnings of the scientific revolution
and the development of philosophy so
anything that happened before that
might have been like colonization but it
wasn't real colonization because it
wasn't systemic
and they actually think this way because
the only thing they give a about is
the prevailing social order
and for them that is the entire world
nothing else has any meaning so they
have
they would they would take things like
that and twist them around and have a
weird explanation for them if challenged
like for example with the greeks well if
the greeks developed reason and they got
it from
the egyptians and then white people had
it white people must have stolen it
that would be the way that they would
would look at that rather than in any
any purpose cases view of how
things actually happen throughout
history and how cultures actually
interact
they can't therefore understand that the
norms of human history have been
colonization
empire building destroying your
neighbors enslaving
whoever you could get a hold of raping
their women these have been the norms of
human history and it's
only been in this modern era that they
hate
and see as having systemic power as a
result
of actually having something like i
guess systemic power
through the power of reason and science
and better ethics and questioning
ourselves
and and setting up rule of law it's only
that we've been
through that that we've been able to get
away from those
horrors of history but they would say
nope systemic power wasn't there when
the mongols conquered
basically everything they didn't have
systemic power they only had regular
power
so it doesn't count it's not the same
thing but what the europeans did
starting in the late 16th century or
15th century
was systemic and that makes it
completely different and that makes it
intolerable
that's genuinely you couldn't possibly
have a more narrow
idiotic and conservative view of history
and i don't mean conservative like you
know
conservatives would be proud to think of
but in the terms of kind of the worst
ramifications of what conservatism can
mean you couldn't have a worse one than
this
this woke thing that calls itself
progressive
yeah let's jump into topic i have later
in my topic list but this is actually a
good time
to introduce it the way this social
justice
capitalized which is a term of art you
define
in the book approaches the world is
essentially hermetically sealed it's a
series of theories
and arguments ungrounded with either
facts or data
and in fact as we just discussed here
they
actively ignore and repress the
application of historical analysis
beyond their own little world empirical
facts
data of any sort and it kind of reminds
me of like
medieval catholicism where you know to
to doubt in any way
or to bring evidence in any way is
actually sinful
and to my mind that strikes me as the
most dangerous than the most absurd
thing about this phenomenon
it is it's a it's a renewal of i mean
you could actually if we wanted to do
the whole game that
you know the academic lingo game we
could call this neo-medievalism
it is an attempt to return to
medievalism and out of modernity
so it's an attempt to reverse the course
of the last 500 years
and it is hermetically sealed in the
sense that
because it thinks in terms only of these
cultural knowledges
that any criticism that comes at it must
be coming from a place
that doesn't properly understand it and
so it
it can dismiss any criticism now it just
simply calls it by names like racist or
whatever it's the application of power
about race or the application of power
about sex and that those are baked into
that white western
hegemonic culture of knowing
and being and thinking in the world and
so what people
really need to take home from this is
that
you know we capitalize the s and the j
for social justice
this is a different way of thinking
entirely it is a completely different
world view it has
it and this is the core part it has a
completely different epistemology in
other words relationship to knowledge
and has a completely different set of
ethics
and those two principles we laid down in
the book the
the postmodern knowledge principle
explain their epistemology it's no
longer truth and falsity that matter
it is instead whether or not the idea is
problematic and how it accords with
somebody's lived experience
specifically of occupying an oppressed
social position
where those have been defined by the
hierarchy of the theory
and the postmodern political principle
defines the ethics
some cultures have been systemically
oppressed others have been
unfairly advantaged and we have to flip
those over
that is in essence their epistemology
and ethics they have a completely
different way of interacting with the
world
that's as foreign as if some
you know aliens that have never seen
sexually reproducing species and don't
have any idea of how anything works
or to suddenly land and they have a
completely different ethical and
completely different
epistemological system it's very
difficult to understand that
indeed and once you do get your head
around i say i will tell you this book
helped me
see it even more clearly than i did
before it's
like what the right it's you know
both insane and dangerous at the same
time
before we leave postcolonial theory
let's talk about
one of the most bizarre manifest
stations of it
which is what you called i think they
probably call it too research
justice
yep the most blatant attempt to cook the
books
in their favor that i'm kind of aware of
research justice is the idea that
research has systemically
excluded certain ideas and certain
voices whether that's because of
methodological rigor or whether that's
because of actual power dynamics doesn't
matter because the view from
postmodernism is that it's all power
dynamics
so they say well historically you know
these white western men came up with
science these white western men define
the canon
of say literature so we're reading
shakespeare
we're you know we're reading milton
we're reading bacon we're reading mark
twain we're you know we're reading
um all of these white western men who
who are the educated
people and the aristocrats i guess in
some sense i had the time and energy to
write
if that's even the right way to put it
and so they
they say that that unfairly biases all
of our knowledge
in the scholarly canon to white western
people so obviously their politics must
be baked into it because that's the
fundamental assumption behind the whole
thing
so what we need to do now is we need to
fix that so we need to stop citing any
white western men
we need to cite black women in
particular and lots of them
we need to cite marginalized voices we
need to stop
teaching from white curricula white
western curricula we need to
insert more materials from other
contexts
and in fact we need to minimize the
amount of white western materials as
they define it so that we can make up
for that
and so you should only cite again black
scholar here's an example an explicit
example of citing that they said that
patricia hill collins
formulation in black feminist thought in
relies very heavily on foucault's
concepts of power but it would be
against research justice or against
intersectionality specifically
to cite michelle foucault when there's
now a black woman who you could cite
instead
and so you have to cite the black woman
so one's identity now
becomes the site for creating citations
and
and what you're going to read what
you're going to teach what you're going
to put in the curriculum
and you can see what's going on because
all of those create professional
opportunities for people oh my papers
have been cited this many times my
papers have not been cited that many
times
and so the it isn't a deliberate attempt
to cook the books
such that the activists because it's not
going to be any black people don't get
don't don't be confused any black women
any black woman who disagrees is not
getting cited let me tell you right now
it's it's a deliberate attempt to cook
the academic books and to skew the
academic canon so that the
activists who have these identity
markers
um get more reputational standing within
scholarship
whereas everybody else gets less uh and
you can you can imagine why they would
want to do that because that's what we
turn to to understand the world
we say oh is there a study i keep
getting asked now
is there a study showing that their
scholar that their their
diversity programs don't work like are
you kidding me of course there's not
they're not going to publish that
yeah it's very interesting and on the
other hand as we know
the legacy effects of systemic racism
which is real have
you know limited to a significant degree
certain minority groups
from participating in the game of
science and it's a good thing
and you know i'm involved in some boards
of advisors at academic institutions we
spent a lot of time thinking about how
to recruit underrepresented minorities
that's a good thing
but to stipulate it as a law as a rule
that you must only quote
people it's nuts right it's like how the
hell does anybody believe that
it's particularly bad in the sciences or
in my own field of mathematics where
in math it's the proof is the proof
that's it that's the whole thing
if you have the proof it doesn't matter
who you are it doesn't actually matter
if a computer came up with it
if you have the proof the thing is
proved and whoever proved it proved it
and it doesn't matter
and that's the basis of you know the
getting say an academic paper in
mathematics
in science it's the same thing it's do
you have the result or don't you have
the result
and to say that you know well now we
have to start skewing this inciting by
race
or by gender starts to massively
undermine that principle that it's
whether or not you have the proof it's
whether or not you have the result and
it doesn't matter who got the proof and
because the proof is true independently
of anybody
or that the uh that the result is
correct
independently of anybody undermining
that belief and turning
that belief into another side of
politics
undermines the ability to rely upon
math and science to to to do things in
the world
is that corruption actually hit
mathematics how could that be
it's not hit research mathematics yet
though i
started to see the calls for it it has
hit mathematics education
hard very hard there are actual programs
in i hear from teachers all the time in
my email but there are actually programs
that have been
installed under under the heading of
ethnomathematics
under a broader curriculum of ethnic
studies in say the city of seattle
but also now i just was talking with
somebody this morning that it's going to
be all throughout unless it gets stopped
it'll be all throughout the state of
california
that there'll be the requirement to put
a social justice focus
in math education and it says things
like that the point is going to be to
make math less individualistic and more
collectivist how do you how do you
determine what's a right answer in math
or more importantly who gets to
determine it
there was even an outcry on twitter last
week with a bunch of freaking math
educators and professionals and even
scholars
trying to argue that two plus two
doesn't equal four because it subjects
other ways other possible values to
exclusion
and i'm not exaggerating that you know
like
what the are you people doing and
the the vector was pure post-modernism
too if you want to know they said well
if you look in base three that you would
write two plus two equals one one
in base three but one one in base three
what we would read is eleven doesn't
mean ten plus one
or eleven it means three plus one that's
what base three means
and so it's like it's literally they
trick themselves with a pun
on two different ways to write the
number four
and they're like that means there are
other possible values
i wish i was making that up i'm so
mad about that that
it's like i can't linger on it too long
because i just start swearing at random
and
it's like i can't believe these are
people with master's degrees
teaching mathematics and designing
mathematics curricula that our states
and cities are actually implementing
and then i get these messages like i'm a
junior high math teacher and i keep
getting these directives we have to put
social justice into the core of our math
education program
so yeah math then i see these
mathematicians and i'm not exaggerating
this and the
notices of the ams the american
mathematical society
writing stuff like exactly what i was
just describing a minute ago they're
writing like
oh well if there's a problem in the
community around mathematics or if
there's a problem in mathematics
education maybe we should be asking the
question if the problem's actually
coming from math itself
and how we engage with math itself and
what we consider to be
objectivity in math and then there's all
these articles out there now about
we need to get away from the presumed
objectivity of mathematics
so it's it's not in like research math
now but it's coming
and it will because it poisons
everything
if they're questioning two plus two
equals four with master's degrees
like i don't even know where you go from
there that's a pretty good one
if you could send me a link to that
tweet i'd love to follow up on that
at a later date i'm going to interject
this here again it's later in my list
but we're getting short on time
i think this is a hugely important topic
and i'm really interested in your
thoughts
on this how many of the people out there
that are
mouthing these things do you think
actually
have the disease versus those who feel
compelled
by the bureaucratic power held by the
disease
to pretend or act as if they
believe it so we have to separate the
world into the p
i mean it's it's kind of like i guess a
tautology as you can see into the people
who are the scholars of this stuff
and the real activists so the ones who
believe it and i think that nearly all
of them believe it
and then the people who are being you
know broader academics so i get emails
from academics literally every day and i
mean lots of them
most days saying i agree with you
and your take and i just wanted to let
you know i support you but i have to do
so in private because i have to keep my
head down so i
you know i play the part i do my act i
pretend that i support this stuff when
i'm at work so i don't lose my job
because
you know i have somebody has to be there
for the kids or somebody has to be
there for my kids you know i have to
keep my job so there's a lot of people
out there who are actually pretending
who are not actually activists and they
just kind of go along with it i don't
think you'll find them being very
strident very often
as for the scholars themselves the
scholars themselves believe this
wholeheartedly
um just like a long time ago christopher
hitchens was asked how many of these
pastors do you really think believe all
this crazy jesus stuff
that they're saying and christopher
hitchens said you know there's always
some grifters
there's always some but that said as a
group
and talking in averages these are the
most painfully sincere people i think
i've ever heard of him or met in my life
and that's true here these people don't
even have a sense of humor they don't
laugh about anything they think laughing
at things is wrong
and so these people are painfully
sincere like so if you ask me about any
of the big ones out there that are
making mad money off of this like robin
d'angelo
or uh ibram candy their best seller
books right now
do they believe it i'm like yo yeah the
100 percent they they're
they are all in on this this is their
faith this is their world view this is
their core of how they think about
things
you can see when they they they butt up
against reality and their eyes kind of
cross a little bit and they don't know
how to handle it so you can tell that
they're grappling with the fact
that the thing that they believe doesn't
quite work and um
you see this a lot so the people who are
actually activists and scholars in this
believe it wholeheartedly but a lot of
people probably the majority of people
supporting it fall into one
one of two groups one is like i describe
those academics who are too afraid to
disagree
so they pretend and another is kind of
uninformed people like
some friends of my kids that have said
things like
yeah you know i'm sharing the hashtags
and the reason is because everybody does
they don't have the slightest idea what
any of it means but you gotta say defund
the police
and it's like well everybody's saying it
and there's a lot of people who are just
not critically thinking about what the
they're saying and
just saying this stuff and carrying
water for
uh extremely radical people thinking
that it's generally
good the third category actually should
add is people who think it can't
possibly be as bad as the things they're
actually saying
they can't actually mean it so i'm gonna
give it a lot of charity i'm gonna
reinterpret it for them and say oh well
they just mean this much more sensible
thing
that is not what they mean and they say
over and over again that it's not what
they mean
so there's a lot of people who support
it because they are
unable to take them at their word
at all even though they say you know on
like almost every page everything they
write how they hate the system
the system systemic power comes from the
system and the system needs to be torn
down and
we need to have a revolution i even saw
a video for like teachers
today that like the first thing that it
showed was how do we start a revolution
in teaching it's like they're not
they're calling for revolution in
everything they do they mean it
yep they are true anti-liberals right
and if we don't
we believe that we're fools frankly
we'll talk a little bit later about what
we might be able to do about it
let's move on to your next topic but in
the interest of time let's try to hit it
quickly
and that's queer theory i'm not going to
say that
the liberation of homosexuals is
actually one of the great wins from
liberalism i recall i grew up as a
working class kid my dad
dropped out of high school after ninth
grade my mother left home when she was
and i had the usual illiberal views
about homosexuality growing up you
didn't almost need to speak about it it
was unspeakable almost right
but i had the good luck to go to work
for a publishing company in the bay area
as a young man
met a bunch of gay folks actually became
friends with him
marched in the second gay pride parade
in san francisco
and at a very young age overthrew my
legacy
homophobia and said it's ridiculous
you know it's a violation of liberal
universalism i didn't have those words
then
gay people should have all rights of
everybody else and
they're just fine what the and it's
clear to me that they're the way they
are because that's the way they are
right and yet that seeming triumph
of universal liberalism which happened
remarkably quickly from
stonewall to gay marriage being
legalized was only 30 years
somehow all that has morphed into this
crazy
well the crazy shit's always kind of
been there a lot of people don't know
that the queer theorists actually
opposed gay marriage from the beginning
and they saw it as a huge
loss for their cause um so you can see
again how they get everything backwards
like i was saying about the colonials
so the deal with with queer theory is
that anything that's normal or normative
must be constraining people and holding
them down in some bad way so you have to
get rid of it
so if you make gay marriage legal now
being gay
is more normative than it was before so
gay people aren't radical
uh divergent things from society any
longer and you take away the radical
power and you sweep them up into the
normative side of society and that's a
failure and it's a loss
so it's a radical rejection of anything
being allowed to be considered
normal and it's a it's a radical
rejection of the idea that categories
can be defined as being stable so to
queer something is to make the
categories around it seem unstable
and laughable so in this case you know
you could say the category of
woman so you could look at lesbians for
example who are in the l
the l of the lgbt thing you could say
well
lesbians are women who are attracted to
women so you have to have a stable
category of woman for lesbian to make
sense
and the queer people would say no that's
not right uh you can't have a
stable category of woman you have to
break that all down and it's just
everybody is a person and everybody can
do whatever they want and
so you can see it's like the thing you
just said made it work oh well they're
they are people who happen to be how
they are and that's fine and so some
people are gay get over it
no big deal it's ridiculous to think
otherwise queer theory gets that
backwards too
because that would make it normal and
normative and that's not okay
they have to make it everything has to
say queer and weird or else it's not
acceptable
interesting and then of course the most
recent manifestation i don't know how
far back this goes
is this literally insane view that
sex itself is not real
what a judith butler said quoted you
quoted in the book
if the immutable character of sex is
contested perhaps this construction
crawled
sex is as culturally constructed as
gender
and perhaps indeed it was always already
gender with
it was always already gender anyway
all that i can't even read the
it's so hard to read judith
butler she's almost impossible
what the hell right my head hurts from
reading it but anyway
basically bottom line she's claiming
well maybe sex itself
is as socially constructed as gender
roles i mean who could believe such
nonsense
right so the that's the idea so the
feminists really wanted to deconstruct
the idea of gender roles being tied so
there's maybe some women don't want to
have
female gender roles okay fine whatever
but then they went further and said so
gender itself has nothing to do with sex
and we're going to completely say that
gender is 100 social constructed
and that's already you're like um
something's getting a bit weird
and then these queer theorists kind of
starting with judith butler with that
question we quoted
started to say well maybe if we really
want to break down the idea of gender
roles and we really want to break down
the idea that gender has any
concrete meaning what we really need to
do is break down the idea that sex has
any meaning at all
other than the imposition say of some
medical
terminology that the doctors put on
people's birth certificates
and so yeah it's this this move it's
like this progressive move from
gender roles being socially constructed
to gender itself being socially
constructed to having to get more and
more and more
radical to break down any normative
categories to say
sex itself is socially constructed
and maybe that's how it really works and
you can like you know you can picture
your mind exploding like wow
maybe that is what a what a radical idea
whoa
and meanwhile the lesbians are over here
like what the
we're women who like women and you know
you're losing us here and so
yeah that's queer theory man that's
queer theory just make anything that's
normal like
bust it up make it weird yeah that's
weird i mean again
at one level i sympathize a little bit
with we need room for diversity of ways
of being in the world
but how is it that people get to these
insane
extrapolations well they believe that
the ideas themselves have lots of power
that structure society again there's
that deep vein of structuralism and
post-structuralism that
fed into the postmodern way of thinking
and they also take a lot from the
critical theory view that there's these
hegemonic forces that are tied up in it
so in other words our post-modern
political and
uh knowledge principles come into into
bearing so they believe that
if we had say biological science saying
that there are actually men and women
and that they're physiologically
different from one another so in other
words biological sex is real
some asshole could use that to justify
sexism so because some asshole could use
it to justify sexism you have to get rid
of it it contains the seeds of hegemonic
power
so it's bad so we're not going to
believe that then you have this whole
rash in the early queer theory
literature and some of the feminist
literature around it
as queer theory was kind of becoming
ascendant saying that what we really
have to do
is get away from the ideas of true and
false even though it's easier to
understand
and start going into this very queer
direction because it's more politically
actionable and that's what we need to
focus on is what's politically useful
for our cause
how cynical as you say right before we
move on from this topic i'd like to
point
people to my friend heather hayne
heather e
hang at heather e haying on twitter
who has said some remarkably intelligent
things
about you know the insanity of claiming
that
sex is not real so i would point you to
her twitter stream and
her appearances on podcasts etc has a
very good
grounding in sense-making about this
topic
let's move on to the next area that you
talk about
which is critical race theory and
intersectionality
you know we certainly have to
acknowledge the hypocrisy about race
under the enlightenment we talked about
before thomas jefferson
people don't know this too much abraham
lincoln and the lincoln douglas debates
famously said that you know the black
man
will never be the social equivalent of
the white man nor should he be etc
there was a lot of retrograde beliefs
and absurd biological explanations
about racial differences and cultural
differences etc
but liberalism has been a
ratchet to gradually bring ourselves
into alignment with our enlightenment
beliefs
and the unjust treatment of racial
minorities especially in the american
context
african-americans was real and it's
still real to a degree but
vastly less so than it was before young
people today don't remember i'd actually
remember
seeing white's only signs on water
fountains in the early 60s
in virginia less than an hour's drive
from washington d.c
tremendous strides have been made and
the liberalism was continuing at least
to improve all this until this invention
of identity politics and the backlash
which has started to occur
i've been predicting since the 1990s
that this ever growing
ratchet of identity politics would
inevitably
lead to the largest identity of all
european americans
catching the disease as well and
asserting themselves
using the same rhetoric and that's what
we're seeing i'm afraid
yeah we don't want that to happen more
than it already is beginning to
and so really this is something i
consider to be a bit of an emergency
uh to try to take away to make people
understand where the critical race
mindset on this comes from
and take that away from them so to kind
of give a very short history we traced
this in the book
of critical race theory it began from
the claim that in the late
16th century going forward that these
biological notions of race and this new
definition of race
came into the world specifically in
order to do racism and slavery and
colonialism and this is true
that it's it's just true uh the way we
thought of race kind of in that racist
past you were just talking about
did come into the picture at that point
and it was
a social construction of race that was
backed up by the authority of bogus
early science and bad claims uh that
were white supremacists in nature
and so the summary of that is that you
can say that these people who wanted to
do slavery and colonialism using
whatever tools they had
available to them at the time put a lot
of social significance into racial
categories
and that ratchet you're talking about
with liberalism has been
ratcheting it out click click click
click you know one turn of the ratchet
after another let's take social
significance
out of racial categories until we
finally get to the point
where we can say things like this is
this is a person who happens to be black
this is a person who happens to be
hispanic this is a person who happens to
be asian and their
their identity is not the first thing
anymore so we're reducing
the social significance in racial
categories which we generally would call
color blindness
when martin luther king said that he
wants to wants to live in a world he has
a dream
that his four little children will be
judged not by the color of their skin
but by the contents of their characters
he's talking about
removing the social significance from
racial categories and then all of a
sudden you have these
identity politicians who are of course
active in parallel to
uh king the the black power movement
malcolm x etc that were pushing this
kind of
positive black identity with a capital b
who wanted to keep the social
significance in race and reverse
the power dynamic assert black power and
keep that there and so and then in the
1990s you have these people that picked
up post-modern theory specifically
kimberly crenshaw
and she has in a paragraph in her most
famous paper called mapping the margins
that we have to take an identity first
approach there's something more powerful
and more meaningful to the sentence i am
black
than to the sentence i am a person who
happens to be black
because of that second sentence puts
their universal humanity first rather
than their identity which is not useful
for identity politics of the radical
sort
she then finishes that paper by saying
we're going to link that to post-modern
theory
to do deconstruction of the power that's
oppressing black people
so what you have then in the long arc is
a history where racial categories were
invented
social significance was put into them in
order to do racist
things liberalism ratcheted that out
over a long
and painful history and then you have
these idiot activists come along and say
you know what let's put social
significance back
into racial categories and see what
happens that's how we're really going to
get liberation
and here we are
yeah i've been long arguing
that america missed a wonderful
opportunity
in the late 60s to unravel our
uniquely bad black white problems
you know martin luther king actually was
on the right track he argued for
essentially
the gradual growing bourgeoisiation
of black people right and in fact people
forget this the remember the monahan
report back in the late 60s where he
gave the famous report on the decline of
the black family and the risks that
made for racial progress and daniel
meinhan the
liberal democrat from new york who
happened to be working for nixon at the
time
and it's now considered racist horrible
etc
but i went back and did some research on
it roy wilkins whitney young and martin
luther king
himself supported that report that was
at a time when out of wedlock births
which was really what moynihan was
focusing on
amongst black americans was 22
now at 70 percent and it seems to me
that this
black power thing and black authenticity
thing which happened right around that
time
diverted what could have been a gradual
melding of black americans into
mainstream society
away from bourgeoisiation and
towards god knows what i'm not really
sure what the alternative really was but
was
essentially a precursor to this critical
race theory thing you're talking about
yeah it's a really unfortunate situation
that um
again we kind of can dip back to that
post-modern view or again we can look at
it from the critical theory perspective
of
you know cultural hegemony and oppressed
groups versus oppressor groups
but within the the post-modern
conception they got infused into this
line of thinking
by kimberly crenshaw very specifically
and some other black feminists around
the same time
you have this idea that each culture is
its own kind of
cultural island it has its own
knowledges it has its own
approaches to to knowing things has its
own ways of being
and those can't be questioned from the
outside in any attempt to change those
is an imposition of power so when you
combine that with that critical theory
view
that impositions of power are the
problem that need to be flipped over all
of a sudden you start to have this
strong push for multiculturalism
rather than a pluralism where you know
you might call pluralism more of a
melting pot approach but people can
still have their own cultural identities
but you're not asserting it as like the
primary thing which is a divisive thing
humans are actually evolved to be tribal
animals
and we're not really good at people
erecting cultural barriers and then
feeling like those people
are people that we can easily relate to
drawing those lines intentionally
is one of the biggest mistakes that
critical race theory is making
and then when you see specifically the
kinds of things that you're talking
about that they want us
they want to define black culture as
something that's in opposition to white
culture
because they claim that white culture is
intrinsically anti-black and a very
cynical and pessimistic description
so they define black culture in
opposition to that so
literally today you know in the past few
weeks i've just seen
things coming out saying that
productivity reliability loyalty
punctuality these kinds of values plus
the science the reason that we've talked
about before
are all white supremacy i've even heard
people in the
in a task force assembled by the
washington state legislature an equity
task force they ran back in january
saying that trying to keep a meeting
schedule and get through an agenda is
white supremacy trying to be productive
is white supremacy so when you start
trying to define a culture in opposition
to
as you phrased it earlier stuff that
works
that most people don't want to associate
with a race at all
you're going to start creating massive
problems and then when you start drawing
these
hard lines and saying you know this is
black culture and it's different than
your culture and we're not the same and
don't try to
don't try to impose on us that would be
colonizing our culture
you're just creating a recipe for
disaster and failure it's
really like the exact wrong way to think
about everything
it's so frustrating yeah
it's crazy and you know the one you gave
the example pissed me off some years ago
the argument against punctuality so for
fun
i wrote an agent-based model that
modeled a company
and you could set how much punctuality
was in the employees
and if you assume that the the work of
the company was significantly done by
people synchronizing and having meetings
you moved the slider on punctuality and
the
effectiveness of the organization
dropped radically and there was a point
where it was a phase change or nothing
got done
right so merely on the empirical
dimension of utility punctuality clearly
has values
god damn it right and anyone who can't
understand that
is just stupid i guess they're
not necessarily stupid some of these
have phds right
which means they got an iq of at least
125 probably
but the disease does something to their
thinking that they can't
even think through the fact that you
know means of production that involve
people synchronizing in time
must lose major effectiveness if we
don't all
honor the value of punctuality yeah they
um
unfortunately human human beings the
smarter you are the more
able you are to convince yourself of
your own and so
often i mean this is probably why this
crap festered in the academy
among a few other problems and values uh
unique to the academy
but the ability to believe i mean
there's a saying you know something so
what is it something so stupid only an
academic could believe it or something
like that
because you're you're more able to
convince yourself of your own
your post-hoc rationalization
and your theoretical ability to convince
yourself of nonsense
is higher when you're smarter um than
when you're not
so uh here we are so
you know stupid in a way it's like i
used to get called too smart for my own
good
when i was a kid all the time and i
never knew what that meant i do now
interesting yeah there's some
interesting psychological lab results
which showed that the
more intelligent on an iq test a person
is the more susceptible they are to
confirmation bias which is interesting
sure because they can make the argument
really quickly for why it must be true
exactly they can rationalize and
basically vibrate off their emotions
and figure it out it's interesting now
it's talking about psychology
as i was reading in your rather
depressing write-up of critical race
theory
it struck me that this has got to be bad
for the mental health of
the groups that are being allegedly
advocated for
right to see that the whole world is
against you that every fine structure of
reality is there to you over in a
fairly permanent way
it's got to be bad for your personal
empowerment
right you know i would turn that around
and say yes we still have
some legacy of racism much less than we
used to the number i use is 8 percent
of white americans are still type 1
racists meaning that
race is an essentialist criteria and
that there are good races and bad races
i use the long-term social science
general survey data on are you opposed
to
intermarriage of somebody close to you
it was 90 percent
1960. it's eight percent today amongst
white folks
that's tremendous progress and the
barriers that exist are overcomeable
if you look at the again empirical data
i know it's it you know it's a violation
to use empirical data against critical
race theory
but you look at how much discrimination
let's say african americans suffer in
the job market
it's around the level they probably need
to go on one more job interview
than white folks get an equivalent job
which is unfortunate and wrong
but isn't enough to stop you from making
progress in the world
in housing you probably got to look at
one maybe two more apartments to
overcome
yes racism in rental housing
these are not obstacles that will stop
you
they're friction but they're not a
pervasive system that you over
so you can't possibly succeed the
rhetoric of critical race theory if i
were
one of the alleged beneficiaries this
perspective would be psychologically
devastating it is it's uh it's like the
opposite
of cognitive behavioral therapy as you
know psychologist jonathan heights
pointed out
it's literally like reverse cognitive
behavioral therapy it makes you more
sensitive
to slights it tends to make you want to
catastrophize
it leads you to believe that the world's
out to get you and so increases paranoia
and cynicism and pessimism and nihilism
it's exactly the opposite of the thing
you want to do now i keep hearing from
from psychologists in fact that are
writing to me and they're talking about
how their
own profession is falling apart or i
hear from people who are in therapy and
maybe there's a cross-racial therapy
therapy situation and now it's like all
power dynamics so now you can even
resolve
the problems that it's creating it's
like this perfect storm of making a mess
that it can can't clean up and then that
it can use
as further fuel to make a bigger mess
the thing is
it's completely backwards in
every way you could possibly
imagine so i often find myself saying
even if
every bit of their diagnosis was correct
and i don't think it is
i think most of it's wrong but even if
it were their prescriptions are all 100
backwards their answers for what to do
with the problem are a hundred percent
backwards
yep certainly strikes me as the case i
mean frankly
i'm kind of old school my advice would
be the same one as
the traditional black grandmother which
is yes there's some discrimination
against you
you got to work a bit harder to beat
whitey right so get out there and study
be diligent be at work five minutes
before the hour
be respectful even if you're a little
cynical about authority which hell i was
i've always had a problem with authority
god damn it right
and that great advice from the
traditional black grandmother is exactly
the right way that
african americans can overcome the
residual racism
that exists in the world and get their
place at the table
it pisses me off i'm like i'm the racist
because okay
if i admit yeah there's there is this
friction you're talking about
in society but i believe that black
people can actually succeed against that
friction and you don't
and i'm the racist like you people
exactly i think i've tried the
rhetorical term of calling these
critical race theory people racists
right
and as you can imagine how well they
respond to that
we can't be racist ah power dynamics but
you're
you're holding black people down so
that's by your definition that's racist
it's like man
this so it's i mean this is like
alice down the rabbit hole
unfortunately we're running out of time
here which is also very interesting
section on feminism
and gender studies but let's skip to
your thoughts and your co-author's
thoughts on what the hell can we do
about this
is there anything that people of good
faith who still adhere to
liberalism and the idea of the
individual and the universal shared
humanity of all humans what can we do
against this tide of crazy
well first let's go ahead and i said
it's a hundred percent backwards just a
second ago let's
let's walk that back to 99. a whole
bunch of nines
the one thing that it's saying that
makes any sense
is could you listen better yes we can
thank you and then everything else that
they say is wrong
so we can listen better and then what we
actually have to do if we want to do
something about this is a number of
things number
one we can listen better number two
we have to actually start reminding
people our schools have systematically
not been teaching american civics for at
least two decades
they just don't teach it people have to
understand how liberal systems work so
we have to start asserting liberalism
we've been able to be comfortable for a
very long time that we just assumed
liberal principles
we have to assert them we have to remind
people what they are we have to get
people to make the arguments for them so
we have to go out and assert them
if you actually want to fight it on a
practical level you have to show up
you have to realize at first there
aren't all that many of the well
until two months ago there weren't all
that many of these people pushing this
very hard
but they're all activists they show up
they want bureaucratic positions they
want to be on the committee
they don't have other important stuff
going on so they're going to make time
to be on the committee to be in the
in the bureaucracy to show up to every
school board meeting
if you aren't going to show up you're
seeding that ground to a relatively
small number of activists
i can't tell you how many school board
meetings i watched in the past two years
where this stuff's getting
ramrodded into our schools and there's
nine people
and there's something like that in the
room it's like where's anybody who
disagrees
well who are the only people showing up
who are the only people who have time
who are the only people who are
interested
activists and that's what you're up
against so if you want to push back
you've got to get informed you've got to
be able to understand their jibber
jabber the book helps with that of
course i've got the website new
discourses dedicated to solving that
problem right now as best i can
you've got to understand the alternative
you've got to understand basic liberal
civics and principles you've got to
understand why we have rule of law
why we do due process why the scientific
processes are important and valuable and
how they help people don't hurt them
why objective standards take cronyism
out of the picture more than they put it
into the picture
you have to understand stuff like that
then you have to show the
up and say it somebody has to show up
and say if nobody's gonna show up and
say it
you're going to have 10 activists show
up and the 10 activists are going to
make the entire decision for your city
and then what now it's policy now it's a
much harder fight
start getting informed get organized and
show up in numbers ideally
and i would add also don't back down to
the right
online recently i actually put together
a good faith discourse
on met it was called the meta discussion
about race how do we talk about race
you can imagine how well that actually
turned out right we got invaded by a
bunch of
quasi-maoists and you know entirely
innocent i would argue
good faith correct way of thinking about
the world was
we should acknowledge current racism
that still exists even at lower levels
and
formally but we should aim for a future
of color blindness i defined it very
carefully
where one's color had no more impact on
your life's trajectory than the color of
your
eyes and i made it very clear that we
were talking about the future
i got attacked vehemently for the word
colorblind and the notion
right but i did not back down
right i
came back with guns blazing and i
thought i did a pretty damn good job
of justifying my position but of course
their style online is very very
vicious
but i think we just got to say hey we're
fighting the equivalent of nazis and
communists here
and so we should not hold back and not
be intimidated by these
yeah the the thing that they have is
name-calling primarily and trying to
make you feel stupid like they have all
these fancy definitions
and trying to say oh you said colorblind
so you're you've committed some
deep offense they're not telling you
that they made up a new definition for
colorblind that that works for their
purposes
nobody in reality except for you know
people who aren't thinking about it very
much
believes that colorblind means i don't
see race so race is completely
irrelevant and it has no impact in the
world that's what they try to get you to
believe
about colorblindness now what it means
is what you said about it has no impact
on the trajectory of your life
that you're not put what it means is in
the formal language i used earlier
is you're not putting social
significance into the racial category
that has some determinant effect on
somebody's abilities
to have access to society that's all it
means
they're playing a word game and using
two meanings of the word at once to try
to call you a name
well guess what once you learn that
that's the game you don't feel
uncomfortable they're like that's racist
to say that and you're like no it wasn't
that's it no it wasn't it wasn't
actually and
just stick to it they have nothing else
they can say the only problem is is that
they'll go after your employer
and that's why when you said you know is
this like the equivalent of nazis and
communists
it's like well they're going after your
employer because they can't
bully you directly so kinda i hear every
day from
hundreds of people who tell me that
they're afraid to speak up
and i try to tell people back the moment
when you realize you're afraid to speak
up is the moment you have to start
speaking up
because this doesn't get better it gets
worse that's the moment you start
speaking up is the moment you realize
you're too afraid to want to speak up
grow a backbone stand up to these people
and this is the message really of the
last chapter of our book
you have the moral high ground if you're
a liberal you have the epistemological
high ground because you believe in
science and you believe
anybody can benefit from science you are
in the position of the so-called right
side of history if you want to steal
their language from them
and they aren't because they don't know
what they're talking about and their
ethics are all kinds of backwards
they have what paul bloom would would
describe is
you know misused empathy their empathy
is bent out of shape and causing them to
do things that
that are are no longer they're not even
empathetic anymore they're cruel
they're that they've left the path of
wisdom as you might
say from like you know you gandalf or
whatever so like somebody who breaks a
thing to see how it works has left the
path of wisdom
they have they've left the path
of wisdom you have the moral you have
the
the epistemological high ground to stand
up to these people
and it's time you started acting like it
all right well we're gonna end it right
there
this has been a remarkably wonderful
conversation james
yeah thanks jim
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern